Hi, everyone
My name is Lingwei Dang from South China University of Technology
I'm here to introduce our work "Diverse Human Motion Prediction via
Gumbel-Softmax Sampling from an Auxiliary Space"
It’s a joint work with Yongwei Nie, Chengjiang Long, Qing Zhang, and Guiqing Li
The task of Human Motion Prediction (HMP) is that given the sequence
of past human poses, we want a model to predict human motions in the future.
It has a wide range of applications in autonomous driving
human-computer interaction
animation creation and so on
There are two typical approaches for HMP
Most previous works perform deterministic HMP that predict only
one motion in the future
However
they ignore the stochasticity nature of human motion, and thus cannot satisfy
those safety-critical applications where forecasting multiple possible pose sequences
is needed
Recently, many diverse and stochastic HMP approaches
adopt deep generative networks such as GAN or CVAE to model
the conditional distribution of future poses given previous ones
They randomly sample latent variables from Gaussian distribution and decode into
multiple possible future motions
Taking CVAE as an example
During training,
the encoder F_Ï• first generates z given x and y
and then the decoder G_Î¸ reconstructs the input y given z and x
after training a CVAE, one can randomly sample latent codes from a prior Gaussian distribution
and then decode the random noises to future sequences
by the CVAE decoder
CVAE maximizes the log-likelihood of data y given x
by introducing an approximate posterior ð‘ž(z|x, y)
and maximizing the evidence lower bound (ELBO)
It models the two distributions of ð‘ž(z|x, y) and ð‘(y|x, z)
by two neural networks F_Ï•and G_Î¸
and estimates their parameters by optimizing the following loss function
However
the CVAE model usually learns an imbalanced multimodal conditional distribution
Latent codes drawn randomly from the prior distribution most probably
correspond to the most likely results
that fall in the dominant mode of the distribution of data
while ignoring other results of low probability but high fidelity
Recently, Yuan et al. proposed a method called DLow sampling
given observed poses, DLow uses a neural network to generate multiple separate
Gaussian distributions
and then samples latent codes from them respectively
However
directly generating Gaussian distributions has two limitations
Firstly,
a network can only generate a fixed number of Gaussian distributions
while there may exist much more modes in the target data distribution
Secondly,
it entangles the performance of diverse prediction with the learning of the network parameters
requiring the latter to consider
all training data and make tradeoffs between them
thus in turn limiting the diverse prediction performance
Different from them
we learn an auxiliary space from the observed poses
then sample points from it and map them to Gaussian distributions
which finally correspond to different modes of the target distribution
Our method disentangles the correlation between diverse prediction and the network parameter learning
and arbitrary number of samples can be generated after the auxiliary space is built
In short,
we propose a post-hoc sampling strategy to sample diverse results with the
pretrained CVAE decoder
On one hand, we design a network N_Î² parameterized by ðœ· that
takes x as input and outputs a base matrix B
where each row of B is a basis vector, and any points in the space can be obtained
by linearly combining these basis vectors
On the other hand,
we use the Gumbel-Softmax sampling strategy to sample a coefficient matrix W
in which
each row contains weights used to combine the basis vectors
Then, we multiply W and B together to obtain a point matrix WB
where each row represents a point
sampled from the auxiliary space
Then, we use another network N_Î³ to further transform the ð¾ points
to Gaussian distributions parameters
A_k and b_k
Finally, we sample latent variables z and decode z_k and x
into a result Ìƒy_k
We impose three kinds of loss functions on the results
to train the proposed sampling framework
First is the Hinge-diversity loss
which explicitly enforce the distance between any pair of generated predictions
to be no less than a user-defined threshold ðœ‚
Second
is the Accuracy loss
that enforces at least one of the predictions to be similar to the ground truth
Third is the KL divergence loss which ensures the model to produce
realistic and plausible results instead of those
with high diversity but are physically invalid
We evaluate our method on the two public motion capture datasets
Human3.6M dataset and the HumanEva-I dataset
And we use five metrics to evaluate our method
APD is the Average Pairwise Distance of results predicted from an input
This metric measures the diversity of the results
ADE computes the Average Displacement Error between the ground truth and the result
most similar to the ground truth
FDE, which stands for Final Displacement Error,
only calculates the distance between the last pose of GT
and the last pose of the most similar result to GT
MMADE and MMFDE are the multimodal versions of ADE and FDE
As shown in this table
our approach outperforms all the other approaches on both diversity metric (APD)
and accuracy metrics (ADE, FDE, MMADE and MMFDE)
To show the quality of the predicted poses
we visualize the generated motions predicted by DLow
GSPS and our method
These two GIF pictures vividly show that our method produces
more diverse results than others
This figure illustrates the holistic views of results
Given one input,
we generate 1000 results and project them into 2D space
Note that DLow can only sample 50 results at a time
To generate 1000 results for DLow, we repeatedly run DLow 20 times
As can be seen, our results occupy the 2D space more evenly
You can scan the QR code for our project
Thank you